Howard R. Garis Papers
Howard R. Garis Papers
1910-1964.
Garis, Howard Roger, 1873-1962.
6 linear ft.
Papers of the American author of children's books, creator of the Uncle Wiggily character and stories. Collection includes correspondence, business and personal letters (1929-1961); typescript books and stories, including those for Uncle Wiggily, and other writings and illustrations relating to various other Uncle Wiggily projects; and memorabilia, including photographs, and financial and legal material.
148997
Biographical History
Howard R. Garis (1873-1962) was an American author of children's books, best known for his Uncle Wiggily stories.
Born April 25, 1873, in Binghamton, New York, the son of Simeon H. and Ellen A. Kimball Garis, he graduated from Binghamton High School and attended Stevens Institute of Technology at Hoboken, New Jersey. From 1896 to 1947, Mr. Garis was a reporter and special writer for the Newark, New Jersey Evening News. His Uncle Wiggily stories first appeared in the News in 1910, were syndicated in 1915, and continued to be published for more than forty years, at one time appearing in one hundred newspapers.
In addition to 35 volumes of Uncle Wiggily stories, Mr. Garis wrote numerous other children's books under his own name as well as under several "house pseudonyms" used by the Stratemeyer Syndicate for its children's series. Among the series Garis contributed to are Tom Swift (as Victor Appleton), the Bobbsey Twins (as Laura Lee Hope), the Motor Boys (as Clarence Young), the Great Marvel series and books featuring Baseball Joe (as Lester Chadwick), and the Camp Fire Girls (as Marion Davidson). He also wrote With Force of Arms (1902), four volumes of the Rocket Riders series, and seven volumes of the Teddy series. His wife, Lilian McNamara Garis, whom he married in 1900, collaborated on several of his books including the Bobbsey Twins volumes.
In addition to his writing, Mr. Garis invented a number of board games, including the Uncle Wiggily Game, Mr. Doodle's Dog Game, Witch Magic Game, Get Well Game, and (with his son Roger) the 100 Red Convertibles Game.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Howard R. Garis papers are divided into four groups: Correspondence, Memorabilia, Writings and Illustrations.
Correspondence, 1929-1961, concerns business and personal matters. Subjects discussed include publication rights, royalties, and Uncle Wiggily books, stories and television programs. Fan letters also are included. Significant correspondents include the Bell Syndicate, Inc., 1929-1960; John J. Clancy, 1952-1953; Winthrop Dakin, 1957-1959; William C. Erskine, 1947-1957; Groban and Rava, 1957; John P. Marquand, 1940; Milton Bradley Co., 1956-1962; Selchow & Righter Co., 1952-1962; Western Printing and Lithographing Co., 1947-1957; and WNJR radio station in Newark, New Jersey, 1948-1950.
Memorabilia, 1910-1964, consists of biographical material, contracts and agreements, income tax returns, earnings statements and photographs. Photo-graphs are of Mr. Garis, his family and friends, and Uncle Wiggily displays.
Writings, 1930-1964, include books, stories, news-paper articles, letters to the editor, autobiographical writings and poems. The Uncle Wiggily manuscripts include a description of the various Uncle Wiggily enterprises, a book, the daily newspaper stories, marionette plays, radio stories and television scripts. Untitled material including fragments of autobiographical material, letters to the editor, news-paper articles, a story and poems is filed at the end of the collection. Most of this material is in typescript and typescript carbon form.
Illustrations, which are oversize, are for unidentified Uncle Wiggily enterprises. Ten pieces, including original drawings, a cutout and photostats of illustrations are included. The artists are unidentified.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type. Within Writings, titled material is arranged alphabetically by title, followed by untitled material in no particular order. Illustrations are in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- Children's; Garis, Howard Roger, 1873-1962 -- Archives.; Authors, American -- Juvenile literature.; Children's literature, Authorship.; Children's literature, American.; Wiggily, Uncle (Fictitious character); Uncle Wiggily series.; Correspondence.; Illustrations.; Memorabilia.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Roger Garis, July 1968; 7/12/62 letter gift of Jill Forman.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1929-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Lilian Garis, 1930; 1947; 2 items (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Financial and legal material
    - Agreements, contracts, insurance policies, 1910-1958 (Box 1)
    - Income tax returns, 1949-1962 (Box 1)
    - Marriage certificate and will, 1946-1957 (Box 1)
    - Receipts, 1954-1962 (Box 1)
    - Royalties and earnings, 1944-1962 (Box 1)
  - Lilian Garis, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Family (Box 2)
    - Friends (Box 2)
    - Howard R. Garis (Box 2)
    - Uncle Wiggily displays and publicity (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Adventures in Secret Valley, book, typescript revised (Box 2)
  - "The Cardiff Giant", newspaper story, repro. (Box 2)
  - Foreign notes, article, typescript carbon (Box 2)
  - "Good Hunting" by Geoff Pouchester as told to Rotun Powwell, Draft A, original typescript; Draft B, typescript carbon, Draft C, original typescript; Draft D, typescript carbon revised; fragments (Box 2)
  - Hard Scrabble Farm Mystery, book, typescript carbon (Box 2)
  - Lobster, story, original typescript (Box 2)
  - Lost Brook, book, original typescript (Box 2)
  - "Professor Jonkin's Cannibal Plant" in Fantastic, May 1963 (Box 2)
  - Round Trip to Venus, book
    - Draft A, typescript carbon (Box 2)
    - Draft B, original typescript (Box 3)
  - Secret Cave, book, typescript carbon (Box 3)
  - Uncle Wiggily stories and enterprises, description and history, original and carbon typescript revised (Box 3)
  - The Uncle Wiggily Book, part of jacket only (Box 3)
  - Uncle Wiggily's Golden Days, book, original and carbon typescript revised (Box 3)
  - Uncle Wiggily Story, daily newspapers
    - 1930, typescript carbon revised (Box 3)
    - 1956
      - January 3-June 9, typescript carbon (Box 3)
      - June 11-September 1, typescript carbon (Box 4)
      - September 3 (Box 4)
    - 1957
      - January -March 23, typescript carbon (Box 4)
      - April 1-June 29, typescript carbon (Box 4)
      - July 1-October 5, typescript carbon (Box 4)
      - October 7-December 21, typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - 1958
      - January 6-April 5, typescript carbon (Box 5)
      - April 7-July 5, typescript carbon (Box 5)
      - July 7-September 6, typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - 1959
      - August-October, typescript carbon (Box 5)
      - November-December, typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - 1960
      - January 4-April 2, typescript carbon (Box 6)
      - April 3-30, June-July, typescript carbon (Box 6)
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - Samples, typescript revised; typescript carbon revised (Box 6)
    - The Bell Syndicate, April 1960; repro. (Box 6)
    - Child Story Syndicate samples, original typescript and repro. (Box 6)
    - Fragments, typescript carbon (Box 6)
  - Uncle Wiggily magazine stories, Pioneer, March-April, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Uncle Wiggily marionette plays, typescript carbon (Box 6)
  - Uncle Wiggily radio stories
    - May, 1930, original typescript revised (Box 6)
    - 1961, original and carbon typescript revised (Box 6)
    - Fragments, original typescripts and carbons, some with revisions; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Uncle Wiggily television programs
    - Description and proposal, holograph and original and carbon typescript (Box 7)
    - Scripts, 1964; undated; typescripts, typescripts carbons, reproduction; some with revisions; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - The Web, story, typescript carbon (Box 7)
  - Untitled
    - Autobiographical material, fragments, original typescript revised; newspaper clipping (Box 7)
    - Letter to the editor, New York Times, August 21, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper story, Newark Evening News, November 18, 1939 (Box 7)
    - Poems, holograph (Box 7)
    - Story, original typescript (Box 7)
  - Unidentified
    - Book, incomplete original typescript, incomplete typescript carbon; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous fragments, typescript (Box 7)
- Illustrations
  - Uncle Wiggily drawings, cutouts and photostats, unidentified artists
    - Pen, ink and watercolor drawing (Package 1)
    - Cutout of a rabbit (Package 1)
    - Pencil sketch of game (Package 1)
    - Chalk drawing of Uncle Wiggily (Package 1)
    - Photostats
      - Dining room (Package 1)
      - Kitchen (Package 1)
      - Uncle Wiggily (Package 1)
      - Skeezicks (Package 1)
      - Pipsisewah (Package 1)
      - Uncle Wiggily, head only (Package 1)